Guide to the Madelyn O. Biggs Papers 1943–2015 (bulk, 1943–1949) PR 335
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Madelyn O. Biggs papers
1943–2015 (bulk, 1943–1949)
PR 335
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
1.667 Linear feet (1 box)
Advertising ephemera, proofs, and tear sheets illustrating the work of commercial artist Madelyn O. Biggs (1923–2016).
Biggs, Madelyn O., 1923–2016
Related Archival Materials
Similar to the Madelyn O. Biggs Papers, but from a slightly later period, the Richard L. Gilbert Advertising Collection (PR-309) contains 90 advertisements and proofs produced by Gilbert's agency in the 1960s and 1970s. And the Bella C. Landauer Collection of Business and Advertising Ephemera (PR-031) consists of circa 800,000 pieces of commercial advertising ephemera.
Arrangement
The Madelyn O. Biggs Papers are housed in a single box of 21 folders, beginning with biographical material on the artist (Folder 1). The subsequent folders are named and sorted alphabetically by the type of product or business advertisements they contain (Folders 2–18). Companies are identified in notes for each folder. A few scrapbook pages and illustration boards follow (Folders 19–20). The portfolio in which the collection came to N-YHS is in Folder 21.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains approximately 100 examples of advertising ephemera, largely in the form of print publication tear sheets and proofs, along with booklets and product packaging, representing the work of commercial artist Madelyn O. Biggs (a.k.a. "Madelyn Oesterling" and "Madelyn O. Hayes"). Biggs created designs for advertising agencies, beverage manufacturers, confectioners, chemical concerns, clothing and fabric mills, hatters, hosiers, underwear makers, fraternal organizations, and utilities. Two purchase orders (Folder 1, below) issued to her by the Metropolitan Edison Company show she was paid $2.50 hourly (in 1947–1948) for “advertising consultation, advertising roughs and layouts, magazine roughs and layouts, [and] finished art work and such other commercial art work as may be ordered” (see Folders 18 and 20 for examples of the work she supplied). The collection also includes a small amount of personal material, and the artist's short essay on the history of advertising (in Folder 1).
Biographical Note
Commercial artist Madelyn O. Biggs was born in Latrobe, Pennsylvania, to Henry R. and Adell (McCracken) Oesterling on 16 September 1923. She graduated from Boyertown High School in Boyertown, Pennsylvania, and later moved to New York City. There she roomed at the Salvation Army’s Markle Evangeline Residence (1941–1945) while attending the Art Career School, located in Manhattan’s famous Flatiron Building.
She began working professionally as early as 1943 under her maiden name, “Madelyn Oesterling.” A note from a pleased officer of L. C. Chase & Company, fabric manufacturers, thanked Miss Oesterling for “a very nice job” that year (see Folder 10 in the container list, below). But in an essay on the history of advertising penned around 1947, she modestly deemed her work of little interest since it kept her hunched “over a drawing table 7 days a week and often 7 nights” (see Folder 1).
On 27 February 1945, Madelyn married in Manhattan her first husband, Alden D. Hayes, and then worked as “Madelyn O. Hayes.” In 1948 she received the Best of Industry Direct Mail Award for her work for Willson Products, Inc., makers of goggles, respirators, gas masks, helmets, sunglasses, and other forms of protective gear (see Folders 1 and 12, below).
Madelyn married her second husband, Richard Ashley Biggs, in Pottstown, Pennsylvania, on 19 November 1949, and then worked as “Madelyn O. Biggs.” She died, age 93, on 4 December 2016.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Estate of Madelyn O. Biggs, 2017.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Biggs, Madelyn O., 1923–2016; Advertisements; Advertising; Commercial artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Ephemera
- Biographical, 1945–2015 (Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes a Christmas card with a self-caricature of the artist at her drawing table, circa 1945–1949; purchase orders issued to Madelyn O. Hayes by the Metropolitan Edison Company, 1947–1948, for roughs, layouts, and artwork (see also Folders 18 & 20); the 1948 Best of Industry Direct Mail Award issued to "Madeline" Hayes for her work for Willson Products, Inc. (see Folder 12); the artist's five-page manuscript history of advertising, circa 1947; stationery of Madelyn O. Biggs, "Commercial Art"; and the Spring 2015 issue of Changing Lives, newsletter of the Salvation Army, Greater New York Division, in which Biggs recounts her time at the Markle Evangeline Residence, 1941–1945.
- Advertising agencies, [1940s] (Folder 2)
  Raymond E. Nelson, Incorporated (New York, N.Y.)
- Beverages, [1940s] (Folder 3)
  Crystal Rock Beverage Company
  Van Ameringen-Haebler, Inc. (New York, N.Y.)
  [See also Folder 19]
- Candy, [1940s] (Folder 4)
  Barricini Candies (Greater New York)
- Chemicals & dyes, 1943–1944 (Folder 5)
  National Aniline Division, Allied Chemical & Dye Corporation (New York, N.Y.)
  Westvaco Chlorine Products Corporation (New York, N.Y.)
- Children’s clothing, 1948 (Folder 6)
  Alpha Mills Corp. (Schuykill Haven, Pa.)
  [See also Folder 20]
- Construction, 1951 (Folder 7)
  Franki Foundation Company (New York, N.Y.)
- Department stores, [1940s] (Folder 8)
  Jeannette (Reading, Pa.?)
- Direct mail advertising, [1940s] (Folder 9)
  Beaumont, Heller and Sperling, Inc. (Reading, Pa.)
- Fabrics, 1943–1944 (Folder 10)
  L.C. Chase & Company (New York, N.Y.)
- Fraternal organizations, 1949 (Folder 11)
  Rajah Temple [Shriners] (Reading, Penn.)
- Goggles, respirators, gas masks, helmets, sunglasses, circa 1948 (Folder 12)
  Willson Products, Incorporated (Reading, Pa.)
- Hats, [1940s] (Folder 13)
  Joseph Kanner Hat Co., Inc. (South Norwalk, Conn.)
- Hosiery, 1948 (Folder 14)
  Infant Socks, Inc. (Reading, Pa.)
  William G. Leininger Knitting Co., Inc. (Mohnton, Pa.)
  Penn Hosiery Mills, Inc. (New York, N.Y.)
- Jewelry, [1940s] (Folder 15)
  C. K. Whitner Co. (Reading, Pa.)
- Laundry, [1940s] (Folder 16)
  Brown’s Laundry (Reading, Pa.?)
- Underwear, [1940s] (Folder 17)
  Arlan’s
  B.V.D.
  Corliss
  Cranbrook Jr.
  Diener Knitting Mills (New York, N.Y.)
  Fairy Silk Mills, Inc. (Shillington, Pa.)
  Insulated Quilted Underwear
  Insulated Thermal Underwear
  Jordan Marsh
  Kress
  Marshall Field & Company
  Royaltex
  Tarleton Tots
- Utilities & infrastructure, 1947–1949 (Folder 18)
  Greater Reading Development Fund (Reading, Pa.?)
  Metropolitan Edison Company (Reading, Pa.)
  Pennsylvania Electric Association
- Scrapbook pages, 1943–1945 (Folder 19)
  Beverages: Van Ameringen-Haebler, Inc. (New York, N.Y.)
  Chemicals & dyes: National Aniline Division, Allied Chemical & Dye Corporation (New York, N.Y.)
  Fabrics: L.C. Chase & Company (New York, N.Y.)
- Illustration boards, [1940s] (Folder 20)
  Children's clothing: Alpha Mills Corp. (Schuykill Haven, Pa.)
  Underwear: C. R. Anthony Co. [men's t-shirts]
  Utilities & infrastructure: Metropolitan Edison Company (Reading, Pa.)
- Portfolio [empty] (Folder 21)
  The collection came to N-YHS in this portfolio.